[中速音乐播放]
[ Mid-tempo music plays ]
♪♪
-卡尔！
-Cal!
-怎么这么晚？
-得躲着老爷子。
-What kept you?
-Had to sneak past the old man.
生日快乐。
Happy birthday.
♪♪
-[轻笑]
-[ Chuckles ]
♪♪
-我想游泳。
-I want to swim.
-什么？
-来吧，露西。
-What?
-Come on, Ruthie.
-你疯了吧，英尼斯！
-You're off your head, Innes!
♪♪
-卡尔！
-Cal!
[咯咯笑]
[ Giggles ]
♪♪
-[咯咯笑]
-[ Giggles ]
-快来，露西！
-Come on, Ruthie!
哇！哇！
-[轻笑]
Whoo! Whoo!
-[ Chuckles ]
♪♪
-中午的航班，
-Flight's at midday,
今晚就能回伦敦了，先生。
so I should be back in London
this evening, sir.
-我以为你要休假一周。
-I thought you were
taking the week.
-是啊，计划有变。
-Aye, well, change of plan.
-发生什么事了？
-What happened?
-主要是我自己的原因。
-Me, basically.
[手机震动]
[ Mobile vibrates ]
[叹气]稍等。
[ Sighs ] Hold on.
喂？
Hello?
-[抽泣]露丝？
-[ Sobbing ] Ruth?
-詹姆斯，你还好吗？
-James, are you all right?
-[抽泣]是卡尔。
-[ Sobs ] It's Cal.
-什么叫是卡尔？
-What do you mean it's Cal?
-[抽泣]
-[ Sobbing ]
-詹姆斯，到底怎么回事？
-James, what is going on?
[敲门声]
[ Knock on door ]
♪♪
[对讲机通话声]
[ Police radio chatter ]
[沉重呼吸声]
[ Breathing heavily ]
-卡尔德警探。不，
你不会想见他的。
-DI Calder. No,
you don't want to see him.
♪♪
-[倒吸冷气]
-[ Gasps ]
♪♪
-他们无能为力。
-There was nothing
they could do.
♪♪
-[颤抖]
-[ Shudders ]
♪♪
-为什么让她靠近尸体？
-Why did you let her
near the body?
-我试图阻止她了。
-Well, I tried to stop her.
-她现在怎么样？
-How is she now?
-[叹气] 她处于休克状态。
-[ Sighs ] She's in shock.
-知道发生了什么吗？
-Do they know
what happened?
-交通组刚开始调查，
-Traffic team are only
getting started,
但看起来像是车辆失控。
but it looks like
he just went off the road.
-怎么失控的？
-How?
-还不清楚，
-We don't know,
但科拉说闻到尸体有酒味。
but Cora thinks she smelled
alcohol on the body.
-[叹气] 好吧。
-[ Sighs ] Okay.
让交通组处理吧。
Let Traffic do their work.
有进展立即通知我。
Tell 'em to call me as soon as
they have something to report.
把露丝带离现场。
And get Ruth
away from there.
我们了解到艾伦在去伦敦前，
Everything we've learned
about Ellen suggests
情绪状态就不太稳定。
she was struggling emotionally
before she left for London.
正在调查具体原因。
We're trying
to work out why.
-如我所言，艾伦的生活方式很放纵。
-Well, as I said, Ellen's
lifestyle was pretty intense.
酗酒、嗑药...
Drink, drugs...
-不，我明白。
-No, I -- I get that.
但我认为这些放纵行为
But I'm starting to think
that the partying
可能是某种症状而非原因。
may have been more
of a symptom than the cause.
我在想真正原因...
I wonder if the cause...
可能是阿克马尔之死。
may have been
Akmal's death.
-为什么这么想？
-What makes you think that?
-有目击者称
-Well, we have
a witness who says
艾伦的问题始于阿克马尔死后。
that Ellen's problems began
just after Akmal died.
-时间点可能只是巧合。
-Well, the timing
could just be a coincidence.
也许那时她正经历其他事。
Perhaps Ellen was going through
something else at that time.
-嗯，有可能。
-Mm-hmm. Could be.
艾伦在这里工作时见过阿克马尔吗？
Did Ellen ever meet Akmal
when she was working here?
-应该见过，
-I suppose she must have,
但她只轮班过几次。
but then, she only did
a couple of shifts.
而且在这期间，
And when she was here,
她几乎没正眼看过阿克马尔。
she barely gave Akmal
a second look.
-所以两人没有...交集？
-So, there was no...
connection?
-我没发现任何异常。
-None that I saw.
-但这不代表她没受到影响。
-But that doesn't mean
she wasn't affected by it.
很多人都被影响了。
Lots of people were.
这里人们的善意，
The kindness
of the people here,
正是支撑我们度过难关的力量。
it's what's
helped us through.
-但她在朗班克的时候，
-But when she was
in Langbank,
艾伦从没跟你提过阿克马尔吗？
Ellen never mentioned
Akmal to you?
-从来没有。
-Never.
-好吧。[轻笑]
-Okay. [ Chuckles ]
只是个猜测而已。
Well, it was just a theory.
很抱歉又提起这些往事。
I really am sorry for
bringing it all back up again.
-没关系。
-It's fine.
-我自己出去就行。
-I'll see myself out.
[开门声，关门声]
[ Door opens, closes ]
♪♪
-[深呼吸]
-[ Breathes deeply ]
-我很抱歉。
-I am sorry.
真心实意的。
I really am.
卡尔是个好人。
Cal was a good guy.
[手机提示音]
[ Mobile chimes ]
可能有点不靠谱，但...
Bit of a rogue maybe, but...
他心地善良。
he had a good heart.
我是说，虽然我俩处不来——
I mean, I'm not saying
me and him got on --
-嘘。先别说话。-喂，是我。
-Shh. Shut up a minute.
-Hey, it's me.
刚去见了博比·贝恩。
Just been up
to see Bobby Bain.
那边肯定有问题。
Definitely something
going on there.
回电给我。
Call me back.
-[轻声倒吸]
-[ Gasps softly ]
我们得去贝恩家。
We need to go to the Bains.
-早。
-Morning.
-你爸妈呢？-还在睡。
-Where's your mum and dad?
-Still sleeping.
-[打响指]嘿。
-[ Snaps fingers ] Hey.
饿不饿？
You hungry?
去主宅吧。
Head up to the big house.
你奶奶会做早餐。
Your gran'll make
some breakfast.
-[呻吟]
-[ Groans ]
天啊。
Jesus.
我都忘了这床有多舒服。
I forgot how comfortable
this bed was.
现在几点？
What time is it?
你还好吗？
You okay?
-我在想她出生那天。
-I was thinking about
the day she was born.
[轻笑]
[ Chuckles ]
分娩了14个小时。
14 hours in labour.
我以为她永远都生不出来了。
I thought she was
never coming out.
-艾伦确实一直让人操心。
-Sure Ellen was always
hard work.
-是啊。
-She was.
你当时震惊吗？
Were you shocked?
-什么？
-What?
-艾伦...
-Ellen...
当他们告诉你她死了的时候，你震惊吗？
When they told you
she was dead, were you shocked?
-天啊。
-Jesus Christ.
这算什么问题？
What kind
of a question is that?
-因为我确实不意外。
-Because I wasn't.
我是说...我当时很麻木...
I mean...
I felt numb and...
你知道的，就是悲伤、愤怒。
you know, grief, anger.
我是说，我...
I mean, I f--
该有的情绪我都有，但是...
I felt all the things
I was supposed to feel, but...
[轻笑]
[ Chuckles ]
我并不感到意外。
I wasn't surprised.
我当时就想"嗯，是啊。确实说得通。"
You know, I thought, "Well, aye.
Aye, that makes sense."
-艾伦不该死的。
-Ellen didn't
deserve to die.
-不，我不是...
-No, I didn't --
我没说她该死。
I didn't say
she deserved it.
[叹气] 她实在太...
[ Sighs ] She was so...
她太不计后果了。
She was so reckless.
[车辆接近声]
[ Vehicle approaching ]
有人来了。
Someone's here.
[开门声]
[ Door opens ]
[羊叫声]
[ Sheep bleating ]
♪♪
-有什么事吗？
-Can I help you?
-你可以先解释下
-Well, you can start
by telling us
为什么卡尔·因尼斯昨晚和你在一起。
why Cal Innes
was with you last night.
-他就是过来喝了几杯。
-Well, he popped by
for a few drinks.
-卡尔·因尼斯...专程...来找你？
-Cal Innes... popped by...
to see you?
-没错。
-That's right.
-没想到你们是朋友。
-Didn't realise
you were pals.
-[嗤笑] 你不知道吗？
-[ Scoffs ] Did you not?
-据我所知，
-Well, as far
as I remember it,
你们当年可是互相看不顺眼。
you two couldn't stand
each other back in the day.
-这有什么问题？
-What's the issue here?
-卡尔的货车昨晚冲出公路了。
-Cal's van went off
the road last night.
就在艾斯镇外。
Just outside of Aith.
-天啊。他没事吧？
-God. Is he all right?
-他死了。
-He's dead.
-老天。
-Jesus.
这太糟糕了。节哀。
I mean, that's awful.
I'm sorry.
他昨晚在这里待了多久？
How long was he here
for last night?
-七点左右到的。离开时...快11点吧。
-Arrived about seven.
Must've left... just before 11.
-所以喝了四个小时？
-So, that's four hours
drinking, then?
-还聊了天。-聊什么？
-And talking.
-About what?
-大部分时间都在说你。
-Mostly he talked
about you.
-卡尔喝了多少酒？
-How much did Cal
have to drink?
-我觉得不该回答这个。-你他妈必须回答！
-Not sure I should answer that.
-Yes, you fucking should!
[深呼吸]
[ Breathes deeply ]
-要我说他走的时候已经喝了不少。
-I'd say he had a fair few
before he left.
-你就这样让他开车？
-And you just
let him drive?
-我劝他别走，让他留宿，
-I told him not to,
I told him to stay the night,
但他根本不听劝。
but he was having
none of it.
-他离开后你做了什么？
-What did you do
after he left?
-在工坊里睡着了。
-Crashed out
in the workshop.
-有人能为你作证吗？
-Anybody vouch for you?
-没有。
-No.
-如果是意外事故
-Why does he need
someone to vouch for him
为什么还需要人作证？
if it was an accident?
♪♪
他来这里干什么？
What was he doing here?
-我们得去趟警局。
-We need to go
to the station.
-我觉得这不是个好主意。
-I'm not sure
that's a good idea.
[叹气] 或许我们可以电话汇报。
[ Sighs ] Maybe
we could call in.
[车门锁提示音]
[ Car lock beeps ]
-如果你周五能多加班两小时
-If you can do an extra
couple of hours on Friday,
那就太好了。
that would be great.
-没问题。
-Yep. No problem.
我听说了卡尔的事。你还好吗？
I heard about Cal.
You okay?
-我没事。我担心的是露丝。
-I'm fine.
It's Ruth I'm worried about.
桑迪说她出现在事故现场。
Sandy said she turned up
at the accident site.
-看到了尸体。-知道怎么发生的吗？
Saw the body.
-Do we know how it happened?
-科拉认为卡尔当时喝了酒。
-Cora thinks
Cal had been drinking.
-[叹气] 有人陪着露丝吗？
-[ Sighs ] Is there anyone
with Ruth?
-我让桑迪照顾她了。
-I asked Sandy
to look after her.
-桑迪？
-Sandy?
-当时没别人了。
-There was no-one else.
-总比没人强吧。
-Better than nothing,
I suppose.
是啊，也只能这样了。
Aye, and there's that.
-他们现在在哪儿？
-Where are they now?
-罗斯玛丽今早保释出来了。
-Rosemary was bailed
this morning.
她暂时住在她妈妈家。
She's staying at her mum's.
艾尔正在去彼得黑德的路上。
Ayre's on his way
to Peterhead.
他们会把他关押到审判开始。
They'll hold him there
until his trial.
-托什，能谈谈吗？
-Tosh, can I speak to you?
-好。派巡警去看看罗斯玛丽，
-Sure. Get Uniform to do
a welfare check on Rosemary,
以防这事引发什么后续麻烦。
just in case there's
any backlash from this.
-明白。
-Will do.
-目前掌握的情况是
-All we know right now
卡尔的货车昨晚某个时候冲出路面。
is Cal's van went off the road
sometime last night.
看起来没有其他车辆涉——
Doesn't look like
any other vehicles were --
-你和萨达特夫妇谈过了？
-Did you speak
with the Sadats?
-今早谈的。怎么了？
-This morning. Why?
-出什么事了？-没什么。
-What happened?
-Nothing.
我在跟进关于艾伦和阿克马尔的一个推测。
I was following up on a theory
about Ellen and Akmal.
怎么？有什么问题？
Why? What's the problem?
-[深呼吸]
-[ Breathes deeply ]
他们的律师刚来过电话。
Their solicitor
just called.
阿齐尔和法丽达认为
It seems Azir
and Farida felt
你问讯时态度咄咄逼人
that you were aggressive
in your questioning
给他们造成了不当压力。
and caused them
undue distress.
-根本不是这么回事。
-Okay, that is not
what happened.
-律师威胁要正式投诉。
-Well, the solicitor's
threatening a formal complaint.
她说以后所有联系
And she says she wants
all future contact
都必须通过她进行。
to be made through her.
你需要收敛一点。
You need to back off a bit.
-等等。
-Hang on.
肯定是我刚离开
他们就打了电话。
They must've made that call
the minute I left.
-说明他们很不安。
-Suggests they were upset.
-我要看阿克马尔·萨达特
事故的报告。
-I need to see the report
on the Akmal Sadat accident.
-为什么？
-Why?
-如果萨达特家
请了律师，
-If the Sadats
are calling in lawyers,
他们肯定在隐瞒什么。
they're hiding something.
-我刚说让你收敛什么来着？
-What did I just say
about backing off?
-我要看报告 哈里。
-I want to see
the report, Harry.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
♪♪
-卡罗琳搞定了。
-Caroline's fixed it.
不会再有突然造访了。
We won't be getting
any more surprise visits.
-我们不可能永远拦着他们。
-也不需要永远。
-We can't hold them off forever.
-We won't have to.
再过几周
这事就会平息。
This will all blow over
in a couple of weeks.
-这事不会平息的 阿齐尔。
-It's not going
to blow over, Azir.
-我们照常生活就行。
-We just carry on
as normal.
-正常？现在这种情况
哪来的正常可言？
-Normal? There's nothing normal
about any of this.
简直疯了。
It's insane.
而且我不会吃那些药！
And I'm not taking those!
你不能一直
用药麻痹我的感受。
You can't keep
numbing me to this.
-我只是想让你保持冷静。
-I'm just trying
to keep you calm.
-我不想冷静！
我跟你不一样！
-I don't want to be calm!
I'm not like you!
你表现得像什么都没发生。
You -- you go around acting
like nothing's happened.
像个机器人！
-那我还能怎么办？！
Like a robot!
-What else can I do?!
啊？
Huh?
不然我怎么收拾
你捅出来的烂摊子？！
How else am I supposed to get us
out of the mess you put us in?!
要是你知道我为保护你
做过的事。
If you knew the things
I've had to do to protect you.
为你付出的一切。
The things
I've done for you.
♪♪
我有个会议。
I have a meeting.
你待在这里
什么都别做 好吗？
I need you to stay here
and do nothing. Okay?
♪♪
[开门声]
[ Door opens ]
-他们失去了孩子 托什。
-They lost a kid, Tosh.
换作是我
If it were me,
the last thing I'd want
最不愿看到的就是
旧事重提。
is for it all to be
dragged up again.
-但至于请律师吗？
-But to call in
their lawyer?
-好吧 确实有点过激，
-Okay, granted,
it's a bit extreme,
但可能他们觉得你...
but then, you know,
maybe they felt you were...
-什么？在履行职责？
-What? Doing my job?
-我只是说说。
-Look, I'm just saying.
很多人都同情法里达和阿齐尔。
There's a lot of folk
who feel for Farida and Azir.
-你的后宫团？
-不 不只是幼儿园妈妈们。
-Your little harem?
-No, not just the nursery mums.
半个岛的人都参加了追悼会。
Half the Isles turned out
for the memorial.
-听着 我不能
就这么放弃
-Look, I cannot
just drop this
因为人们同情他们。
because people
feel sorry for them.
-我知道 但是...
能不能委婉点？
-Yeah, I know, but...
maybe go gently, eh?
[开门关门声]
我们还得在这儿生活呢。
[ Door opens, closes ]
Like, we have to live here.
-我晚点再跟你说。
-I'll talk to you later.
露丝 我对卡尔的事
感到非常遗憾。
Ruth, I'm so sorry
about Cal.
-你们得把鲍比·贝恩
带回来问话。
-You need to bring in
Bobby Bain.
-为什么？
-Okay, why?
-因为他昨晚
和卡尔在一起。
-Because he was
with Cal last night.
-他们在农场喝酒。
-They were drinking
at the farm.
-不只是喝酒。
听着...
-Not just drinking.
Listen...
-是我。
刚去找过鲍比·贝恩。
-Hey, it's me.
Just been up to see Bobby Bain.
他肯定有问题。
Definitely something
going on there.
给我回电。
-卡尔什么时候留的这个？
Call me back.
-When did Cal leave this?
-昨晚
离开农场之后。
-Last night,
after he left the farm.
-你给他回电话了吗？
-Did you call him back?
-我今早才看到留言。
-I didn't pick it up
until this morning.
重点是 卡尔发现了
鲍比的某些事，
Point is, Cal found out
something about Bobby,
而且我们询问时
鲍比表现得很可疑。
and Bobby was shifty
when we spoke to him.
-什么时候问的？
-什么？
-When?
-What?
-你们什么时候
询问鲍比的？
-When did you speak
to Bobby?
-今天早上。
-This morning.
-[深深叹气]
-[ Exhales deeply ]
能借一步说话吗？
Could I have a word?
-露丝 我很抱歉...
-Ruth, I'm sorry about...
-我们这是在浪费时间。
-We're wasting time here.
越早对鲍比采取行动...
-你感觉怎么样？
The sooner we move on Bobby...
-How are you feeling?
-我什么感觉？
-关于卡尔的事。
-How am I feeling?
-About Cal.
-等你们把鲍比·贝恩
抓回来
-Well, I'll feel
a whole lot better
我心情就会好多了。
when you bring in
Bobby Bain.
-以什么罪名？
-还问罪名？！
-For what?
-For what?!
你没听到留言吗？
Did you not hear
the message?
卡尔刚发现他的秘密，
Cal finds out
something about him,
转头就开车冲出了公路？
next thing, he's driving
his van off the road?
-你和詹姆斯谈过了吗？
-Have you spoken to James?
-还没
我没时间。
-No, I --
I haven't had time.
-你不觉得应该
和他谈谈吗？
-Well, don't you think
maybe you should?
他现在可能需要朋友。
He probably needs
a friend right now.
-我更想专注在
鲍比身上。
-I'd rather just focus
on Bobby.
所以到底抓不抓他？
So, are we bringing him in,
or -- or what?
-我觉得应该等
-I think we should wait
科拉和事故调查组的报告。
for Cora and the Crash
Investigation team.
-天呐 真是够了。
-露丝 听我说。
-Oh, for Christ's sake.
-Ruth, listen to me.
你别插手这件事。
You need to stay
out of this.
-好吧。
-Okay.
算了 当我没说。
Know what? Forget it.
-露丝？
-Ruth?
-新药片的化验结果显示
纯度相当高。
-Lab results on those new pills
show they're pretty high grade.
-所以呢？
-And?
-在咱们这儿可不常见
我是说...
-Well, it is unusual
for up here. I mean...
[摔门声]
[ Door slams ]
-桑迪，带她去詹姆斯·英尼斯那儿。
-Sandy, take her
to James Innes.
陪着她，别让她惹麻烦。
Stay with her
and keep her out of trouble.
-好的。
-Sure.
她会没事吧？
She going to be okay?
-我不知道。
-I don't know.
[狗叫声]
[ Dog barking ]
-嗨，我得走了。
-Hi. I've got to go.
厨房里有给你准备的吐司和鸡蛋。
There's toast and eggs
in the kitchen for you.
-我不饿。
-I'm not hungry.
-嘿...
-[抽泣声]
-Hey...
-[ Sniffles ]
-怎么了？
-What's the matter?
-只是在想艾伦的事。
-Just thinking about Ellen.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
我知道，这太难受了。
I know, I know.
It's awful.
我能做点什么吗？
Is there anything I can do?
-能转点钱给我吗？
-Can you transfer me
some money?
-[嗤笑] 昨天刚给你30英镑。
-[ Scoffs ] I gave you
30 quid yesterday.
-算了算了，当我没说。
-It's fine, it's fine.
Doesn't matter.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
[手机提示音]
我给你转50，行吗？
[ Mobile chimes ]
I'll ping 50 over, okay?
-谢谢。
-但我得走了。
-Thanks.
-But I need to go.
晚点见。
-再见。
I'll see you later.
-See you.
[开门关门声]
[ Door opens, closes ]
[手机震动声]
[ Mobile vibrating ]
-喂？
-Hello?
-卡尔死了。
-什么？
-Cal's dead.
-What?
-昨晚从农场回来时货车翻了。
-Last night. Crashed his van
on the way back from the farm.
今早警察来找我问话。
Police came to see me
about it this morning.
-为什么？
-因为他昨晚和我在一起。
-Why?
-'Cos he was with me last night.
-什么叫和你在一起？
-What do you mean
he was with you?
-别问了。
-Never mind.
他们很可能会找你问话。
There's a good chance
they'll want to speak to you.
要是真找你，别提我
If they do,
you don't mention me
也别提那笔钱的事。
and you don't mention
the money.
-那我该说什么？
-随便你。
-Well -- well, what do I say?
-I don't care.
只要别扯上我就行。
Just as long as you
keep my name out of it.
-鲍勃！鲍勃！
-Bob, Bob!
♪♪
-不想进去就别勉强。
-You don't have to go in
if you don't want to.
我们可以去别的地方。
I mean, we can just go
somewhere else.
我爸去世时，我谁都不想见。
You know, when my da died,
I didn't want to talk to anyone.
只想躲起来。
Just wanted to hide away
from the world.
但悲伤需要有人分担。
But the thing about grief is,
it needs to be shared.
一个人扛不住的。
You can't do it
on your own.
-天！好吧我去。
-Jesus! Fine, I'm going.
只要你能闭嘴。
Anything to shut you up.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
-[深呼吸]
-[ Breathes deeply ]
♪♪
[对讲机通话声]
[ Police radio chatter ]
[模糊不清的低语声]
[ Quiet, indistinct chatter ]
♪♪
-露丝。
-Ruth.
♪♪
怎么会发生这种事？
How did this happen, eh?
我们该怎么办？
What are we going to do?
♪♪
-[抽泣] 过来。
-[ Sobbing ] Come here.
-[急促的呼吸声]
-[ Breathing shakily ]
♪♪
-比利？
-嗯？
-Billy?
-Aye?
-把希瑟·贝恩的电话给我。
-Get me Heather Bain's number.
-我不明白。
-I don't get it.
这是阿齐尔
和法里达家的厨房。
It's Azir
and Farida's kitchen.
所以呢？
So what?
-在操作台上。
冰箱旁边。
-On the worktop.
By the fridge.
那个清洁工具箱。
是不是你的？
The cleaning caddy.
Isn't that one of yours?
-看起来是。
-Looks like it.
可能是我
落在那里的。
Guess I must've
left it there.
-但这张照片拍摄于
阿克马尔出事当天。
-But this photograph was taken
on the day of Akmal's accident.
那天你去过萨达特家吗？
Were you at the Sadats'
house that day?
-没有！
-No!
但工具箱可能是
前几天落下的。
But I probably left the caddy
there a few days before.
-有没有可能
-Is there any chance
埃伦那天去过萨达特家？
that Ellen was at the Sadats'
house that day?
-没理由去啊。
-Don't see why
she would've been.
-或许他们临时
找她顶班没告诉你。
-Well, maybe they got her in
for a shift without you knowing.
-[嗤笑] 不可能。
他们不是那种人。
-[ Scoffs ] I doubt it.
They're not the type.
再说埃伦干活
也不怎么利索。
Plus Ellen was a pretty
useless cleaner.
你问这个干嘛？
Why are you asking, anyway?
-我觉得阿克马尔之死
对埃伦影响很大。
-I think Akmal's death
had an impact on Ellen.
这可能是她
后来消沉的原因。
I think it's the reason
why she was struggling.
她提起过这事吗？
Did she ever talk about it?
-当然提过。那段时间
大家都在议论。
-Well, aye. For a while, it was
all anyone was talking about.
-嗯 除此之外呢？
-Yeah, but beyond that.
你觉得她心里
一直放不下这事吗？
Did you ever get the sense
that it was on her mind?
-埃伦不是那种
沉溺悲伤的人。
-Ellen wasn't one
for dwelling on sad stuff.
有派对或帅哥时
更不会多想。
Not when there was a party
or a boy to think about.
-我不确定。
-I don't know.
我觉得埃伦比大家
想象的更敏感。
I think Ellen was a lot deeper
than people seem to think.
-哦！抱歉 我得走了。
-Oh! Sorry, I need to go.
这样吧——
I'll tell you what --
我回家确认下
工具箱是否少了一个。
I'll check if I'm missing
a caddy when I get home.
-谢谢。
麻烦你了。
-Thanks.
I appreciate that.
[开门关门声]
[ Door opens, closes ]
[手机拨号声]
[ Mobile dialling ]
-麦凯布。
-嗨，比利，是我。
-McCabe.
-Hi, Billy, it's me.
需要你帮我调取一些通话记录。
Going to need you to pull
some call records for me.
♪♪
[鸟叫声]
[ Birds calling ]
-你还好吗？
-You okay?
-我处理不了别人的悲伤。
-I can't do
other people's grief.
-[深深呼气]
-[ Exhales deeply ]
-他怎么样？
-How is he?
-詹姆斯？詹姆斯他...
-James? James is...
彻底崩溃了，
well, he's wrecked,
不过身边有可靠的人陪着。
but he's got good people
around him.
不像你。
Unlike you.
-我没事。
-I'm fine.
-艾玛去朋友家住了。
-Amma's gone
to stay with a pal.
想暂时离开一段时间。
Decided to take
some time out.
-明白了。
-I see.
-就是需要些空间，懂吗？
-Just need some space,
you know?
听着，那晚的事我很抱歉。
Look, I'm sorry
about the other night.
是我太过分了。
I was out of order.
-没关系。
-不，有关系。
-It's okay.
-No, it's not.
确实过分。我不该那样反应。
It's not. I shouldn't
have reacted like that.
我不该发火的。
I shouldn't have got angry.
-你和爸爸感情很深。
-You and Dad were close.
我理解。
I get it.
-我生气不是因为这个。
-That's not
why I got angry.
我觉得你可能是对的。
I think you might
be right.
-关于什么？
-About what?
-关于爸爸和斯特拉·奎恩。
-About Dad
and Stella Quinn.
♪♪
-[吉他弦音]
-[ Strumming guitar strings ]
♪♪
-这些日期都确认过了？
-And those dates
are confirmed?
-看起来是的。
-It looks like it.
-怎么回事？
-What's going on?
-我调取了萨达特一家
-I pulled the call records
for the Sadats
以及希瑟和艾伦
and Heather and Ellen
在阿克马尔·萨达特死亡前后的通话记录。
from around the time
Akmal Sadat died.
-为什么？
-Why?
-因为我觉得阿克马尔的死有蹊跷
-Well, because I think there's
something about Akmal's death
他们没告诉我们真相
they're not telling us,
我认为希瑟和埃伦都牵涉其中
and I think Heather and Ellen
were involved.
-我——
-I --
-听着 先听我说完 就一分钟 求你了
-Look, just -- just listen to me
just for a minute. Please.
事故发生后的第二天
The day after the accident,
埃伦给希瑟打了七次电话
Ellen called Heather
seven times.
而在那天之前
Now, up until that day,
希瑟能接到埃伦一周一次的电话就算幸运了
Heather was lucky to get a call
from Ellen once a week.
阿齐尔的通话记录显示
Azir's records show
在阿克马尔死后那几天
that he and Heather
talked 16 times
他和希瑟通了16次电话
in the days
after Akmal's death.
有些通话时长超过一小时
Some of those calls
lasted over an hour,
但希瑟坚称事发当天
and Heather claims
neither she nor Ellen
她和埃伦都没在萨达特家工作
was working at the Sadats' place
on the day of the accident,
可我们在现场发现了她的清洁工具箱
but we have her
cleaning caddy at the scene.
这怎么解释？
What's it doing there?
-阿克马尔的死因调查过了
-我知道
-Akmal's death was investigated.
-I know.
-警方、法医、儿童服务机构
-Police, pathologist,
child services,
甚至我们办公室都认定这只是场悲剧
and even my office decided it
was nothing more than a tragedy.
-也许你们搞错了
-为什么？
-Maybe you got it wrong.
-Why?
就因为几通不寻常的电话？
Because of some
unusual call patterns?
当时死了个孩子
A child had died.
对所有人来说都不是寻常时期
It wasn't a normal time
for anyone.
-对阿齐尔·萨达特而言
更是至暗时刻
-And for Azir Sadat,
it was the worst time.
这个男人失去了儿子
The man lost his son.
无法想象如果是我孩子会怎样
I can't imagine how I would feel
if that was my child,
但我很确定
but I am pretty sure
在那之后的日子里
the last person I'd be calling
in the days after it
我最不可能联系的就是清洁工
is my cleaner.
-你应该专注追查杀害埃伦·奎恩的真凶
-I think you need to focus
on who killed Ellen Quinn.
-哈利 我正是在这么做！
-Harry, I am!
我们知道埃伦去伦敦前就深陷困境
We know Ellen was struggling
before she went to London.
现在又发现阿克马尔的忌日对她很重要
Now we know the date of Akmal's
death was important to her.
我觉得这就是关键
I think this could be it.
-她为他感到难过
-She felt sorry for him.
-或者她心怀愧疚
-Or maybe it was guilt
she felt.
也许她知道些内情
Maybe she knew
something about it.
也许她知道真相
Maybe she knew the truth,
而这可能就是她的死因
and maybe that's
what got her killed.
-你这全是猜测
-That's a lot
of maybes in there.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
-这是什么时候的事？
-很久以前了
-When was this?
-Ages ago.
我大学第一学期 当时回家住了一阵
It was my first term at uni.
I was back home for a bit.
-你看到什么了吗？
-And did you see anything?
-只记得斯特拉经常出现
-All I remember is
that Stella was around.
经常在教堂 有时在家里
A lot. At the kirk,
sometimes at the house.
我虽没亲眼所见 但今早和琼聊过
I didn't see anything, but
I spoke to Jean this morning,
据说她有次去牧师住所
and apparently, she walked in
on Dad and Stella one day
撞见父亲和斯特拉在一起
at the manse.
我想这就是他们分手的原因
And that's, I think, what put
an end to their relationship.
-持续了多久？
-How long did it go on for?
-几个月吧，最多两个月。
-Couple of months.
Two at the most.
后来斯特拉突然就不来了。
One day, Stella just
stopped coming.
-为什么？
-不知道。
-Why?
-No idea.
再见到她时，她正在教堂和基兰结婚。
Next time I saw her, she was
at the church marrying Kieran.
-他提起过她吗？
-Did he ever say
anything about her?
-老天，从没有。
-God, no.
不过从那以后他确实和贝恩斯家保持距离。
He did keep his distance from
the Bains after that, though.
-为什么？
-Why?
-你没资格进这里，而且...
-You have no business
being in there, and...
-搞什么鬼？
-我受够了！
-What the hell?
-I'm not putting up with it!
太荒唐了！滚出我家！
This is outrageous!
Get out my house!
-我不是故意惹你生气。
-怎么回事？
-I didn't mean to upset you.
-What's going on?
-他想抹黑我哥哥的名声！
-He's trying to blacken
my brother's name!
尸骨未寒，
Body's not even cold,
这混蛋就指控他贩毒！
and this bastard's
accusing him of dealing!
-我没说卡尔在贩毒。
-I didn't say
that Cal was dealing.
-放屁！他刚问我有没有见过卡尔带药片。
-Bullshit! He's just asked me
if I ever saw him with pills.
-什么？为什么这么问？
-晚点再说。
-What? Why would you ask that?
-Let's talk about it later.
-没什么好说的。
-There's nothing
to talk about.
-你为什么要问卡尔是否贩毒？
-Why would you ask
if Cal was dealing?
-我在他房间发现了这些。
-I found these in his room.
几个月前岛上开始流通新型毒品。
New drugs started coming
onto the Isles a few months ago.
我们不清楚幕后黑手是谁，
We've no idea
who's behind it,
但毒贩用的都是这种包装袋。
but whoever it is,
they use bags like these.
-就这？
-你们只有这点证据？
-That's it?
That's all you've got?
-他说得对，证据确实不足。
-Well, he's got a point.
It's not much.
-这些药片来自阿伯丁。
-The pills are sourced
in Aberdeen.
我在缉毒队的线人证实了这点。
My Drug Squad contact
down there confirmed it.
还有证人证实每月都有固定运毒——
And I have a witness who says
the pills come in every month --
规律运输意味着——
regular, which means --
-好了，我明白了。
-Yes, all right. I get it.
能...能让我们单独谈谈吗？
Could you... could you
give us a minute?
好。
Yeah.
[脚步声渐远]
[ Footsteps retreating ]
-我记得桑迪·威尔逊上学时的德行。
-I remember Sandy Wilson
when he was at school.
当年是个小混蛋，现在还是。
He was a wee shit then
and he's a wee shit now.
-詹姆斯，卡尔多久运一次货去阿伯丁？
-James, how often was Cal
taking your stock to Aberdeen?
-不清楚，不算频繁。
-Oh, I don't know.
Not that often.
-每月一次？
-Once a month?
-你居然向着他说话！
-You're taking
his side on this!
-我保持中立。
-I'm not taking
anyone's side.
桑迪可能有点操之过急，
Sandy might've jumped
the gun a bit.
但卡尔确实有问题。
I know that Cal
was up to something.
老实说，
Let's face it.
这并不意外，对吧？
It's not really
a surprise, is it?
-我哥哥是好人。
-My brother was a good guy.
-是啊，他努力过。
-Yeah, he tried to be.
听着，现在这些都不重要。
Look, none of this
is important right now.
我会和桑迪谈。
I'll talk to Sandy.
-你要找的是尼尔·贝恩。
-It's Neil Bain
you want to talk to.
-我为什么要找尼尔·贝恩？
-Why do I need
to talk to Neil Bain?
-他之前总在这附近晃悠。
-He was always
hanging around here.
我警告过卡尔别靠近他。
I told Cal to stay clear.
要是有毒品交易，准是他搞的鬼。
If there's dealing,
he'll be behind it.
[嗤笑]
[ Scoffs ]
前几天他和另一个人来过这儿。
Him and the other one
were here the other day.
两个油头粉面的家伙。-另一个人是谁？
Couple of fly men.
-What other one?
-当我是傻子吗。
-Think I'm bloody stupid.
-詹姆斯，另一个人是谁？
-James, what other one?
-博比·贝恩。
-Bobby Bain.
-艾伦，你留下来陪詹姆斯？
-Alan, will you stay
with James?
我们得找到尼尔·贝恩。
We need to find Neil Bain.
-等等，我们找他是为了...？
-Wait, we're looking
for him because...?
-因为我想知道
-Because I want to know why
他和博比·贝恩为什么和卡尔混在一起。
he and Bobby Bain
were up here with Cal.
车钥匙？
Keys?
-或许该通知托什。
-Maybe we should
let Tosh know.
-为什么？难道要她批准？
-Why? Er, do you need
to ask her permission?
-不是。只是觉得该向她汇报进展。
-No. I just think I should call
her and keep her up to speed.
-行啊，随你便。
-Fine, go ahead.
Do that, then.
我可不想你挨训。
I'd hate for you
to get a row.
-这招对我没用。
-That's not going to work.
我又不是十二岁。
I'm not 12.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
-[叹气]天啊。
-[ Sighs ] Christ.
我来负责问话。
I'll do the talking.
-行，但车得由我开。
-Fine, but I'll do
the driving.
钥匙呢？
Keys?
[汽车锁哔哔声]
[ Car lock beeps ]
[羊叫声]
[ Sheep bleating ]
♪♪
-嘿，你没事吧？
-Hey, you all right?
♪♪
-你看过这个吗？
-Have you seen this?
-别管它。-别管它？
-Don't worry about it.
-Don't worry about it?
上面说埃伦和斯特拉坎家的女孩
It says that Ellen
and the Strachan girl
跟这个...怪胎搞过邪教。
were in a cult
with this... freak.
-埃伦不可能参与这种事。
-Ellen wasn't
into that stuff.
-你怎么知道？
-How would you know?
-她是有很多毛病，但不至于这么蠢。
-She was a lot of things,
but she wasn't stupid.
-那昨晚怎么回事？
-So, what about last night?
-什么意思？-你问我什么意思？
-What do you mean?
-What do I mean?
我是说卡尔·英尼斯那档子事！
I mean, what the hell
happened with Cal Innes?
-我不知道。
-I don't know.
-一个人和你喝酒后死了，
-A man dies after spending
the night drinking with you,
你就只会说"我不知道"？
and all you can say is,
"I don't know"?
-那你想让我说什么？
-What else
do you want me to say?
-[嗤笑]
-[ Scoffs ]
你看起来不太担心。
You don't seem
too concerned.
-斯特拉和基兰似乎好些了。
-Stella and Kieran
seem better.
-怎么个好法？
-Better how?
-至少他们开始交谈了。
-Well, they're talking
for a start.
-是啊，希望他能开导开导她。
-Aye, well, let's hope
he can talk some sense into her.
那姑娘需要有人提醒她谁才是家人。
That girl needs reminding
who her family is.
-你这话什么意思？
-What's that supposed
to mean?
-意思就是她没资格和诺克斯家来往。
-It means she had no right
breaking bread with the Knoxes.
-"来往"？
-"Breaking bread"?
[轻笑]
你是认真的吗？
[ Chuckling ]
Are you serious?
她只是去找那个男孩谈话。
She went over
to talk to the boy.
-你在为她辩护？
-You're defending her?
-她刚失去女儿啊！
-She just lost
her daughter!
-所以我们就该拱手让出
-And that means
we have to hand over
多年奋斗的一切？
everything
we've worked for?
-是我奋斗的一切！
-Everything I worked for!
是我！
Me!
别担心。
Don't worry.
我们已经没什么可让的了。
There's nothing left
for us to hand over.
♪♪
-对了卢，要不要买个小面包
-Right, Lou, what are you
thinking about a wee bun
路上吃？
for the way home, eh?
嗯？怎么样？
Huh? That sound good?
[轻笑]
[ Chuckles ]
哦。
Oh.
法里达。
Farida.
♪♪
你还好吗？
Are you all right?
♪♪
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
[手机铃声]
[ Mobile rings ]
喂。
Hey.
[狗吠声]
[ Dog barking ]
-记住，由我来交涉。
-Remember,
I'll do the talking.
-明白。
-你只是来观察的。
-Understood.
-You're just here to observe.
-只听不说。
-Seen and not heard.
-基本就是这个意思。
-That's the gist of it.
[敲门声]
[ Knock on door ]
-卡尔德探长。
方便进来吗？
-DI Calder.
Mind if we come in?
我们需要谈谈你和卡尔的关系。
We need to talk to you about
your relationship with Cal.
-卡尔？
-Cal?
-卡尔·因尼斯。
你们是朋友。
-Cal Innes.
You two were friends.
-不算朋友。
只是认识而已。
-Not really.
I knew him, that's all.
-"认识"？！
-"Knew him"?!
所以你听说他死了？
So, you heard he died?
-嗯，他出了意外。
-Yeah, he was in
an accident.
-谁告诉你这是意外的？
-Who told you
it was an accident?
-[嗤笑]
-[ Scoffs ]
我不...我不知道。
就...听说的。
I don't -- I don't know.
I ju-- I just heard.
-你上次和卡尔联系是什么时候？
-When did you last
speak to Cal?
-呃，我不记得了。
-Er, I don't know.
很久之前。
Ages ago.
我们关系没那么近。
我其实不太了解他。
We weren't that close.
I never really knew him.
-真的吗？嗯。
-Really? Hmm.
因为他弟弟说你和他有生意往来。
'Cos his brother said that you
and him were dealing together.
-生意？
什么生意？
-Dealing?
Dealing what?
-药片。就是卡尔每个月
-Pills. The ones that Cal was
bringing in from the Mainland
从大陆带过来的那些。
every month.
-我完全不知情。
-I don't know
anything about that.
-好吧。行。
-Okay. Right.
那我们就这么办吧。
Well, here's
what we'll do, then.
这位威尔森警探会调搜查队过来。
DC Wilson here's
going to call in a Search team.
他们会彻底搜查这里，
We'll get them
to go over the place,
与此同时，
and while
they're doing that,
我们会让因弗内斯的技术小组
we'll get the IT team
from Inverness,
检查你的通话记录、短信、
they'll start going
through your calls, texts,
聊天记录和上网历史...
chats, internet history...
-什么？我又没犯法。
-What? I haven't
done anything.
-那你更不用紧张了，对吧？
-Well, you have nothing
to worry about, then, have you?
不过我们还有个目击证人。
But then, of course,
there's the witness.
-什么目击证人？
-What witness?
-哦，就是威尔森警探找到的那位。
-Oh, the -- the one
that DC Wilson found.
指认你就是
The one who identified you
卖药给他们的那个人。
as the person
that sold them the pills.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
听着，我没卖药。
Look, I didn't sell them.
可能送过几片，
Maybe gave a few away,
但药都是卡尔带来的。
but Cal was the one
that brought them up here.
-所以是你和卡尔合伙？
-So, it was you and Cal?
-主要是卡尔。
-Mostly Cal.
-那鲍比呢？
-What about Bobby?
我们知道你和他昨天联系过卡尔。
Look, we know that you and him
spoke with Cal yesterday.
也知道卡尔昨晚去过贝恩农场，
We know that Cal was up
at the Bain farm last night,
所以你最好老实交代
so you need to start
by telling me
鲍比·贝恩在这件事里的角色！
what Bobby Bain's part
in all of this is!
-鲍比和这事没关系。
-Bobby didn't have
a part in this.
-打电话叫搜查队。
-别，等等。
-Make the call.
-No, no. Wait, wait.
好吧。
Right.
行，我说。
Okay. Fine.
♪♪
[叹气]
[ Sighs ]
鲍比几天前才入伙。
Bobby only got onboard
a few days ago.
-怎么入伙的？
-Came onboard how?
-他说有资金。
-He said he had some money.
想让我们运更多货，但卡尔拒绝了。
He wanted us to bring in
a bigger stash, but Cal refused.
他没答应鲍比。
He turned Bobby down.
-那昨晚卡尔为什么和鲍比在一起？
-So, why were Cal and Bobby
together last night?
-我...我不知道。
-I -- I don't know.
-具体涉及多少资金？
-How much money
are we talking?
-看起来很多。
-Looked like a lot.
-所以你看到了？
-So you saw it?
-是的。
-Yeah.
装在一个袋子里，
全是现金。
It was in a bag,
full of cash.
我估计有几千块。
Thousands, I reckon.
♪♪
[关门声]
[叹息声]
[ Door closes ]
[ Sighs ]
-[唱歌声]
*你的脚去哪儿了*
-[ Singing ]
* Where's your foot gone? *
*你的脚呢*
* Where's your foot? *
哦，妈妈来了。
Oh, here's Mummy.
嘿。
-嗨。
Hey.
-Hi.
[叹息声]
[ Sighs ]
她在哪？
-[叹息声]
Where is she?
-[ Sighs ]
[路易斯轻声细语]
[ Louise coos ]
-她说想和你谈谈。
-Says she wants
to speak to you.
但是托什，那个...
温和点行吗？
But, Tosh, like,
go easy, would you?
-好的。
-明白。
-Yeah.
-Okay.
-你还好吗，法里达？
-How are you doing,
Farida?
唐尼说你想见我？
Donnie says
you wanted to see me?
-他是在这里学会骑自行车的。
-He learned to ride
his bike here.
我和阿齐尔带他来的。
Me and Azir brought him.
那辆自行车是橙色的。
It was orange,
the bike.
他特别喜欢。
而且学得特别快。
He loved it.
And he was so quick.
才学了一次就能
绕着我们又笑又闹了。
One lesson and he was racing
around us, laughing.
[深呼吸]
[ Breathes deeply ]
我还能闻到他身上的味道。
I can still smell him.
如果我闭上眼睛
集中精神，
If I close my eyes
and focus,
就能闻到他头发上
阳光的气息。
I can smell the heat
on his hair.
[抽泣声]
[ Sobs ]
都是我的错。
It was my fault.
-什么错，法里达？
-What was your fault,
Farida?
我睡着了。
I fell asleep.
我当时太累了。
I was so tired.
阿齐尔给了我
这些新药片，
And Azir had given me
these new tablets,
可能是我吃太多了，
but I must've
taken too many
或者之前吃过
又忘记了。
or maybe I forgot
and I'd taken some before.
我情绪总是不稳定。
I struggle with my moods.
阿齐尔帮我控制。
Azir helps me
manage them.
我是被尖叫声惊醒的，埃伦，
I only woke up because
she was screaming, Ellen,
在花园里尖叫。
in the garden.
希瑟正俯身对着我。
And Heather was leaning
over me.
摇晃着我。
Shaking me.
我脑子完全不清醒。
I couldn't get
my head to work.
她不停地说："是阿克马尔"
And she was saying,
"It's Akmal."
我说："不可能
他在自己房间"
And I said, "No.
He's in his room."
然后她说...
"哦，法里达"
And she said...
"Oh, Farida."
这时我才明白
埃伦为什么尖叫。
And I saw why Ellen
was screaming.
[啜泣]她在花园尽头...
[ Sobbing ] She was at
the bottom of the garden...
跪在地上。
on her knees.
而他...
就躺在她怀里。
And he was lying
across her.
我漂亮的男孩...
已经死了...
My beautiful boy...
had died...
孤零零地死在那片湖里...
alone in that loch...
而我却浑然不知地睡着。
and I'd slept through it.
-法里达...
-Farida...
发生这样的事
我真的很抱歉。
I am so sorry
this happened.
我需要问你
几个问题，可以吗？
I have to ask you
a few things, okay?
希瑟和艾伦发现阿克马尔后
发生了什么？
What happened after Heather
and Ellen found Akmal?
-阿齐尔回到家，他哭着
对我大喊大叫。
-Azir came home, and he was
crying and shouting at me.
说这都是我的错。
Saying it was all my fault.
-然后呢？
-What happened then?
-她接手了局面。
-She took over.
希瑟让阿齐尔
打电话叫救护车。
Heather told Azir
to call the ambulance.
她让他告诉救护人员
说事发时他在现场。
She told him to tell them that
he was there when it happened.
我们会说当时
一不留神没看住他，
We would say, we took our eyes
off him for a few minutes,
他可能自己跑进花园
掉进了湖里...
and he must've got into
the garden and into the loch...
-为什么？为什么要
这么说？
-Why? Why were you
to say that?
-因为她说
我们会失去一切。
-Because she said
we'd lose it all.
那些药片。
不是正规处方开的。
The pills.
They weren't prescribed.
是阿齐尔给我的。
Azir was giving them to me.
他会丢掉工作。
He'd lose his job.
我会被起诉，祖玛
也会被带走。
I'd be prosecuted, and they'd
take Zuma away from us.
所以...我们对所有人
都撒了谎。
So, we lied...
to everyone.
我们背叛了儿子。
We betrayed our boy.
-过来。过来。
-Come here. Come here.
-[抽泣]
-[ Sobbing ]
-没事的。
没事的。
-It's all right.
It's all right.
♪♪
-法里达？
-Farida?
你在哪？
我开始担心了。
Where are you?
I'm getting worried.
你——你需要——
You -- you need the --
[车辆接近声]
[ Vehicle approaching ]
♪♪
-肯定是
艾伦的钱。
-It has to be
Ellen's money.
-我们还不确定。
-We don't know that
for sure.
-但贝恩斯家
确实很困难。
-Well, we know the Bains
are struggling.
农场已经
多年没有盈利了。
The farm hasn't
made profit for years.
说真的，鲍比·贝恩斯
哪来的钱
I mean, come on, where's
Bobby Bain going to find cash
涉足毒品生意？
to get into
the drug business?
-听着，就算是艾伦的钱，
-Look, even if it is
Ellen's money,
她被杀前
就已经丢了。
she lost it
before she was killed.
-豪威尔说的。
也许她骗了他。
-Says Howell.
Maybe she lied to him.
可能她逃脱后
又拿回了钱。
Maybe she picked up the money
after she got away from them.
遇到鲍比
就被他谋财害命。
She runs into Bobby
and he kills her for it.
也许卡尔昨晚
就是发现了这个。
Maybe that is what Cal
found out last night.
如果卡尔盯上了鲍比，
And if Cal was onto Bobby,
这足以成为
他灭口的动机。
that's reason enough
for him to want him dead.
-首先得证明
确实是艾伦的钱。
-Well, first, we need to prove
that it is Ellen's money.
鲍比也可能
有其他资金来源。
I mean, Bobby could've got it
from another source.
-那就要查他的
银行记录。
-Then we need to access
his bank records.
-那你得去找托什谈谈。
-Then you'll need
to talk to Tosh.
-桑迪！
-Sandy!
-这事闹得太过了。
-This has gone too far.
-他是为了我才去那儿的。
-He was there
because of me.
♪♪
卡尔去见博比是因为我有事要查。
Cal went to see Bobby because
I needed to know something.
只是些不能告诉你的事，但...
Just something
I can't tell you about, but...
[叹气]
[ Sighs ]
他昨晚去那儿
He went there last night
是因为想帮我。
because he was wanting
to help me.
现在他却死了。
And now, he's dead.
那个...愚蠢可恨的毒贩混蛋死了，
That... stupid, infuriating,
drug-dealing arsehole is dead,
我很确定是我的错。
and I'm pretty sure
that it's my fault.
♪♪
所以我必须这么做。
So, I really need
to do this.
你明白吗？
Do you understand?
-我会尽力帮忙。
-I'll see what I can do.
好的。
Okay.
♪♪
-我想让你知道我做那些事
-I want you to know
that I only did what I did
只是为了保住我的家人。
to keep my family.
-你隐瞒了你儿子的死因。
-You lied about
your son's death.
-当时我们深受打击，
-We were in shock,
所有决定都是希瑟做的。
and Heather was making
all the decisions.
我们当时很害怕。
We were frightened.
-艾伦对此怎么看？
-What did Ellen
think about it?
-我觉得她想说出真相，
-I think she wanted
to tell the truth,
但希瑟不让。
but Heather
wouldn't let her.
希瑟掌控着一切。
Heather controlled it all.
从我们开始撒谎那刻起就被她拿捏了。
As soon as we started lying,
she had us.
-拿捏？
-Had you?
怎么个拿捏法？
In what way?
-追悼会刚结束她就开始了。
-It started just
after the memorial.
说需要些钱。
Said she needed some money.
说得像是借款。
Made it sound like
it was a loan.
-她勒索你们？
-She blackmailed you?
-一直到现在。
-Has been ever since.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
即便如此，这仍改变不了
Even so, that still
doesn't change the fact
你和法里达撒谎的事实。
that you and Farida lied.
-那是个意外。
-It was an accident.
是我们永远无法释怀的悲剧。
A tragedy
we'll never get over.
怎么发生的？为何发生？
How it happened?
Why it happened?
都只是细节。
Just details.
-阿克马尔是你们的家人。
-Akmal was your family.
他是你们的儿子。
He was your son.
他值得比肮脏的掩盖更好的对待。
And he deserved better
than a sordid cover-up.
你说的那些细节是他生命的记录，
Those details you talk about
were the record of his passing,
本应得到应有的尊重。
and they should have been
treated with the proper respect.
-[叹气]
-[ Sighs ]
♪♪
-我真不明白怎么会漏掉这个细节
-I don't understand
how we missed this.
他们接受过问询 社会服务部也调查过他们
They were interviewed. Social
Services investigated them.
-这确实是场悲剧
但受害者都是好人
-It was an awful thing,
and it happened to nice people.
没人愿意往最坏处想
Nobody wants
to think the worst.
-我们需要重启案件调查
-We'll need
to reopen the case.
-法里达·萨达特的证词
-谢谢
-Farida Sadat's statement.
-Thanks.
现在能通知格兰特去封锁萨达特家吗？
Now, can you tell Grant to go
and secure the Sadat house?
法医有发现随时通知我们
Let us know if Forensics
find anything.
-明白 你们为什么要搜查他们家？
-Sure. Why are you
going over the house?
-他们的车也要做痕迹检测
-I want their car
processed, too.
-可他们已经认罪了啊
-But they've already
admitted to it.
-我知道
-I know.
-如果你们在找阿克马尔死亡的证据
-If you're looking
for evidence of Akmal's death,
那都是几个月前——
-重点不是阿克马尔
it was months --
-This isn't about Akmal.
是艾伦
It's about Ellen.
阿齐尔刚刚承认
Azir just admitted
艾伦曾想说出车祸真相
that Ellen wanted to tell
the truth about the accident,
而且我们知道她遇害当天试图联系过他
and we know she tried
to call him on the day she died.
艾伦对萨达特家是个威胁
Ellen was a threat
to the Sadats.
有发现立即通知我？
You call me
if they find anything?
-好的 你去哪？
-Aye. Where will you be?
-找希瑟·贝恩
-With Heather Bain.
-鲍比的银行记录刚传过来
-Bobby's bank records
have just come through.
这家伙破产了
This guy's broke.
-这...我是说鲍比·贝恩绝对不可能
-Does it -- I mean, there's no
way Bobby Bain's managed
靠自己筹到这么多钱
to raise thousands
off his own back.
-但不代表钱来自艾伦
-Ah, doesn't mean
he got it from Ellen.
-是 但概率越来越大了
-No, but the odds
are shortening.
-找到了
[餐盘碰撞声]
-There you are.
[ Plates clink ]
-就算他经济困难
-Even if he is struggling,
真会为钱杀害亲侄女吗？
would he really kill
his own niece for money?
贝恩家毕竟...
-这些是伦敦的交易记录
I mean, the Bains...
-These are London transactions.
-什么？
-What?
-所有借记卡消费
-All of these
debit card payments.
呃 最近一笔是4月18日
Er, last transaction
was the 18th of April.
那是艾伦回来前三天
That is three days
before Ellen came back.
-鲍比去过伦敦？
-Bobby was in London?
-我得打个电话
-I need to make
a phone call.
[车辆驶近声]
[ Vehicle approaches ]
[车门猛关声]
[ Car door slams ]
-他们失去了孩子！
-They lost a child!
五岁的儿子
A five-year-old son.
而你做了什么？
敲诈他们
And what did you do?
You blackmailed them.
-[嗤笑] 不知道你在胡说什么
-[ Scoffs ] Don't know
what you're on about.
-少装糊涂 法里达全告诉我了
-No, don't give me that.
Farida told me everything.
-呵 别太相信法里达的话
-Oh, I wouldn't put too much
store in what Farida says.
她经常神志不清
She gets confused.
-你闭嘴！
-Don't you dare!
轮不到你对别人指手画脚
You don't get to make
judgments on anyone,
在你做出那种事之后就别想了。
not after what you did.
-我做的事？[轻笑]
-What I did? [ Chuckles ]
哦，是啊，你现在对她充满同情，
Oh, aye, you're full
of sympathy for her now,
但如果那天到场的是你们，
but would you lot
have been so understanding
你们会这么善解人意吗？
if you'd turned up
that day?
湖里的孩子和崩溃发疯的母亲。
A kid in the loch and a mother
blasted out of her mind.
她告诉你发生了什么？
She told you
what happened?
法里达不记得发生了什么。
Farida doesn't remember
what happened.
-但她记得你勒索了他们。
-She remembers
you extorted them.
-我没勒索任何人。
-I didn't extort anyone.
但你知道吗？
But do you know what?
也许我真该那么做，
Maybe I should have,
因为要不是我，他们早就失去一切了。
because without me,
they'd have lost everything.
我做了件好事。-[嗤笑]
I did a good thing.
-[ Scoffs ]
-那艾伦呢？-她怎么了？
And what about Ellen?
-What about her?
-她需要你的时候你在哪？
-Where were you
when she needed you?
当她为那件事痛苦挣扎的时候。
When she was struggling
with what happened.
-那时你做了什么？-我一直都在艾伦身边。
What did you do then?
-I was always there for Ellen.
-你把她送去了兰班克。-因为她需要帮助。
-You sent her to Langbank.
-Because she needed help.
-因为你需要让她闭嘴。
-Because you needed
to shut her up.
你把她交给了阿齐尔·萨达特
You handed her over
to Azir Sadat
就是想让他想办法封住她的嘴。
because you wanted him to find
a way to keep her from talking.
-艾伦永远不会说出去的。
-Ellen was never
going to talk.
她崩溃不是因为阿克马尔。
She didn't break down
because of Akmal.
是，她很痛苦。我们也是。
Aye, she was upset.
We all were.
但那不是她离开的原因。
That's not why she left.
-那她为什么离开？
-Then why did she leave?
-谁知道呢？！
-Who knows?!
谁在乎啊？
And who cares?
艾伦就是个噩梦。
Ellen was a nightmare.
我巴不得摆脱她。
I was glad to see
the back of her.
♪♪
[手机铃声]
[ Mobile ringing ]
♪♪
-亚历克斯？
-Alex?
-法医有新发现。
-Forensics have
found something.
[警用对讲机杂音]
[ Police radio chatter ]
-给你。
-Here you go.
-我刚和我的警探聊过。
-So, I've just spoken
to my DC.
我让他向艾伦的室友核实
I'd asked him to check
with Ellen's flatmate
是否能确认
to see if she could confirm
鲍比·贝恩18号那天在艾伦家。
that Bobby Bain was at Ellen's
on the 18th.
-然后呢？-她无法确认。
-And?
-And she couldn't.
-那就这样吧。-还没完。
-Well, then, that's that.
-Well, not quite.
我的警探发现了当天的报案记录。
My DC found an incident
report from that day.
有人报警去艾伦公寓。家庭纠纷。
A call-out to Ellen's flat.
Domestic disturbance.
-邻居报的警。-有具体细节吗？
A neighbour called it in.
-Were there any details?
-有。她说艾伦当时在和个年长男人争吵，
-Oh, yes. She said that Ellen
was arguing with an older man,
但警察赶到时那人已经走了。
but he'd gone by the time
the Uniforms showed up.
-我们不确定是鲍比干的
-Well, we don't know
it was Bobby.
-不 邻居用手机拍到了那人
-Yes, we do. The neighbour
snapped the guy on her phone
我团队已确认是鲍比
and my team
have ID'd Bobby.
♪♪
-阿齐尔 我想问艾伦·奎恩遇害当晚
-Azir, I want to ask you about
the night Ellen Quinn died.
你和她有过接触吗？
Did you have any contact
with her that night?
我们在你车里发现了这条毯子
We found this blanket
in your car.
能确认是你的吗 阿齐尔？
Can you confirm
it's yours, Azir?
其颜色材质与我们在
The colour and the fabric
are similar
艾伦头发里发现的纤维吻合
to fibres we found
in Ellen's hair.
对此你有什么解释？
You got any
thoughts on that?
-没有
-No.
-我们还在你车里发现了血迹
-Well, we also found
blood traces in your car.
法医团队认为血迹较新鲜
Our Forensic team believe
they're relatively fresh.
形成时间不超过一周
No more than, say,
a week old.
-我没杀她
-I didn't kill her.
-但你和她在一起？-是的
-But you were with her?
-Yes.
-就在她遇害当晚？
-On the night she died?
-我没接电话 她就找上门来
-When I didn't answer her call,
she came to the house.
-当时几点？
-What time was that?
-很晚了 她浑身湿透还受了伤
-It was late.
She was wet. Injured.
-她为什么找你？
-Why did she come to you?
-她要钱
-She wanted money.
说惹上麻烦必须离开设得兰
Said she was in trouble
and had to leave Shetland.
我说没钱 她就发火了
I told her I didn't have any.
She started getting angry.
法里达在睡觉 我不想惊动她
Farida was asleep.
I -- I didn't want her upset.
-然后你怎么做的？
-So, what did you do?
-答应明早想办法筹钱给她
-I told her I'd try and get her
some in the morning.
然后她就走了
And then she left.
-你说过艾伦想揭露阿克马尔真相
-You told me Ellen wanted
to tell the truth about Akmal.
-我们都想 -但希瑟阻止了你们？
-We all did.
-But Heather stopped you?
-对
-Yes.
-可如果艾伦真站出来
-Still, if Ellen did choose
to come forward,
会是个大麻烦
that would be a problem.
-我没杀艾伦
-I didn't kill Ellen.
-我不信你 阿齐尔
-I don't believe you, Azir.
如果艾伦来过又离开
You see, if Ellen turned up
at your house and then left,
为何证据显示她上过你的车？
how come we have evidence
that she was in your car?
她威胁要揭发阿克马尔对吧？
She threatened to tell the truth
about Akmal, didn't she?
告诉你她准备站出来作证
She told you she was
going to come forward.
-没有
-No.
-她就站在你家门口
-And there she was,
on your doorstep,
威胁你的家人 -我没杀人
threatening your family.
-I didn't kill her.
-那她怎么上的你车？！
-Then how did she get
into your car?!
-因为我担心她！
-Because I was worried
about her!
那么晚 她独自一人
It was late.
She was on her own.
她走后我开车追了上去
When she left,
I drove after her.
-你追她？
-You chased after her?
-只是想确保她安全
-To -- to make sure
she was okay.
追上后让她上了车
I caught up with her.
Told her to get in.
-她答应了吗？
-是的。
-And did she?
-Yes.
-后来发生了什么？
-And then what happened?
-我问她想去哪里。
-I asked her where
she wanted to go.
我说可以带她去任何地方。
I told her
I'd take her anywhere.
-她想去哪里？
-Where did she want to go?
艾泽尔。
Azir.
你把艾伦带去哪儿了？
Where did you take Ellen?
♪♪
-鲍比·贝恩在撒谎。
-Bobby Bain is lying.
-他们都在撒谎。
-They're all lying.
艾伦那晚回家了。
Ellen came home that night.
♪♪